Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Professional Papers, 1909-1990; Series II
  - Saarinen, Eero
    - Awards
      - Building-specific awards
        - University of Chicago, Law School
          - American Institute of Architects and Chicago Chapter and Chicago Association of Commerce and Industry, Honor Award, 1960 (Box 676, Folder 85)
          - Municipal Art League of Chicago, Citation for Civic Art, 1960 (Box 673, Folder 38)
        - Vivian Beaumont Theatre and Library-Museum of the Performing Arts at Lincoln Center
          - Concrete Industry Board of New York, 1965 (Box 701, Folder 221)
          - Concrete Industry Board of America Award: dinner program, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 32)
        - Yale University, David S. Ingalls Hockey Rink: Architectural League of New York, Honorable Mention in Engineering [to Severud-Elstad-Krueger Associates], 1960 (Box 673, Folder 38)
    - Clippings
      - Eames, Charles, 1941-1981, undated (Box 18, Folder 33)
      - Girard, Alexander, 1949, undated (Box 18, Folder 34)
      - Knoll, Florence, 1949, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 35)
      - Foreign publications, 1957, 1958, undated (Box 18, Folder 36)
      - Office personnel, 1956, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1952, 1956-1959 (Box 18, Folder 38 - 42)
      - General, 1960-1961 (Box 20, Folder 43 - 45)
      - AIA R-17 summer seminar, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 46)
      - Architectural Association, London, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 47)
      - Harvard fifth conference on urban design, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 48)
      - Hoffman, Julius, 1960-1961 (Box 20, Folder 49)
      - Institute of Contemporary Art exhibit, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 50)
      - MIT Alumni Association visit, 1955-1956 (Box 20, Folder 51)
      - Playboy article, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 52)
      - Rice University lecture, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 53)
      - Schmidt-Grohe, Johanna, 1960-1961 (Box 20, Folder 54)
      - Shokokusha publication, 1960-1961 (Box 20, Folder 55)
      - Sports Illustrated, 1960 (Box 20, Folder 56)
      - Sweet Success article, 1960 (Box 20, Folder 57)
      - Tange, Kenzo, 1955 (Box 20, Folder 58)
      - University of California visit, 1956, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 59)
      - Venezuelan Society of Architects exhibition, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 60)
      - Yale School of Architecture dean selection, 1956-1958 (Box 20, Folder 61)
      - Zodiac article, 1959 (Box 20, Folder 62)
    - Juries
      - American Institute of Architects Honor Awards, 1955-1956 (Box 20, Folder 63)
      - Homes for Better Living Awards, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 64)
      - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 65)
      - Porcelain Enamel Design Competition Awards, 1955-1956 (Box 20, Folder 66)
        - Additional material (Box 680, Folder 124)
      - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 1956-1957 (Box 20, Folder 67)
      - R.S. Reynolds Memorial Award, 1958-1959 (Box 20, Folder 68)
    - Pamphlet: Office of Strategic Services: "Army Personnel Control," designed by Saarinen, 1944 (Box 20, Folder 69)
    - Presentations and lectures
      - Architectural Association, London, 1956-1957 (Box 21, Folder 70)
      - Campus planning presentation, University of Michigan, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 71)
      - "The Design of Industrial Plants" conference, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 72)
      - Dickinson College Arts Award, 1959-1960 (Box 21, Folder 73)
      - Economic Club of Detroit, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 74)
      - "Golden Proportions", undated (Box 21, Folder 75)
      - Schoner Wohnen Congress, Munich, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 76)
      - University of Pennsylvania, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 77)
      - Voice of America [radio program transcript], "What is Modern Architecture Trying to Achieve in the United States?", 1958 (Box 21, Folder 78)
    - Reference files on art and architecture
      - Artists' promotional materials and correspondence
        - Albers, Josef, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 79)
        - Azaz, Henri, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 80)
        - Carr, Sally Swan, 1957, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 81)
        - Condon, Rudolph, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 82)
        - Gabo, Miriam, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 83)
        - Pattison, Abbott, 1956, 1958, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 84)
        - Sowers, Robert, 1954, 1955 (Box 21, Folder 85)
        - Steichen, Edward, 1932, 1957, undated (Box 21, Folder 86)
        - Steinberg, Saul, undated (Box 21, Folder 87)
        - Mural selection for Milwaukee County War Memorial, 1954, 1958-1959, undated (Box 22, Folder 88)
        - General artists' promotional materials and correspondence, 1954-1962 (Box 22, Folder 89 - 90)
        - General mural correspondence and photographs, undated (Box 22, Folder 91)
      - Reference drawings
        - Commercial, historical, classical, undated (Box 23)
        - Comparative campuses: schools/colleges, other Saarinen designs, shopping centers, miscellaneous, undated (Box 24)
        - Duomo, Florence, undated (Box 25)
        - Estates, undated (Box 26)
        - Palaces, churches, undated (Box 27)
      - Research files on facades
        - Photographs of facade details, undated (Box 679, Folder 123)
        - Portfolio of facade studies [printed], undated (Box 683, Folder 148)
      - Teaching slides, undated (Box 22, Folder 92 - 107)
        - Additional slides, part 1 (Box 705)
        - Additional slides, part 2 (Box 706)
        - Additional slides, part 3 (Box 707)
        - Additional slides, part 4 (Box 708)
    - Writings
      - Published articles
        - "Our Epoch of Architecture," Journal of the American Institute of Architects, 1952 December (Box 28, Folder 108)
        - "The Challenge to the Arts Today," Yale Daily News, 1953 (Box 28, Folder 109)
        - "Architecture of the Future," Cleveland Engineering, 1953 May (Box 28, Folder 110)
        - "The Six Broad Currents of Modern Architecture," Architectural Forum, 1953 June (Box 28, Folder 111)
        - Forward to The City by Eliel Saarinen, 1957 (Box 28, Folder 112)
        - "Campus Planning: the Unique World of the University," Architectural Record, 1960 November (Box 28, Folder 113)
      - General writings
        - "The Changing Philosophy of Architecture", 1954 June (Box 28, Folder 114)
        - "Main Currents of Mid-Century Architecture", undated (Box 28, Folder 115)
        - On Frank Lloyd Wright, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 116)
        - [On Mies van der Rohe, FLW, Philip Johnson, SOM] (dictated), undated (Box 28, Folder 117)
        - General statement about architecture (dictated), 1959 (Box 28, Folder 118)
        - "General statement about the sculptural, curved structural shapes that we have been involved with [...]", undated (Box 28, Folder 119)
        - Miscellaneous statements about buildings [A-I], Circa 1958-1961 (Box 28, Folder 120)
        - Miscellaneous statements about buildings [I-Y]; statements by associates about buildings, Circa 1957-1961 (Box 28, Folder 121)
  - Saarinen, Eliel
    - Drawing: aerial plan of Cranbrook grounds, undated (Box 29)
    - Photographs
      - "Eames' dad (4 years) by Gran'Dad Eliel" [reproduction of pencil sketch], undated (Box 30, Folder 122)
      - Portrait of Eliel Saarinen, undated (Box 30, Folder 123)
    - Publications
      - Cranbrook Academy of Art [various publications], 1931-1942 (Box 30, Folder 124)
      - "Eliel Saarinen In Memorium," Arkkitehti, 1950 (Box 30, Folder 125)
      - "Eliel Saarinen, Master of Design," Pencil Points [offprint], 1936 September (Box 30, Folder 126)
      - Exhibition catalogue on Eliel Saarinen [in Russian], 1957 (Box 30, Folder 127)
      - Funeral [press release], 1950 (Box 30, Folder 128)
      - Kalevalaseura [Finnish brochure on Finnish National Center], 1921 (Box 30, Folder 129)
      - Moderne Bauformen [with architectural designs by Eliel Saarinen], 1950 (Box 30, Folder 130)
      - Munksnas-Haga och Stor-Helsingfors, 1915 (Box 30, Folder 131)
      - "Museum and Library, Cranbrook Academy of Art, Bloomfield Hills, Mich.," New Pencil Points, 1943 (Box 30, Folder 132)
      - Pro Helsingfors, 1918 (Box 30, Folder 133)
    - Project photographs and photoreproductions
      - Cranbrook
        - Cranbrook Academy of Art, Bloomfield Hills, MI
          - Aerial photographs and topographical map, 1935, undated (Box 30, Folder 134)
          - Exteriors, undated (Box 30, Folder 135)
          - Milles fountains, undated (Box 30, Folder 136)
          - Museum and library
            - Exteriors (including Milles fountains), 1951, undated (Box 30, Folder 137)
            - Floor plan and section, undated (Box 30, Folder 138)
            - Interiors, undated (Box 30, Folder 139)
            - Rendering, Circa 1940 (Box 30, Folder 140)
          - Paintings by Zoltan Sepeshy, undated (Box 30, Folder 141)
          - Sculptures (includes sketch studies for Milles fountain), undated (Box 30, Folder 142)
          - Slides: school, gardens, exhibition hall views, undated (Box 30, Folder 143 - 144)
          - Weaving studio: interior, undated (Box 30, Folder 145)
        - Cranbrook School for Boys, Bloomfield Hills, MI
          - Exteriors, undated (Box 30, Folder 146)
          - Interiors, undated (Box 30, Folder 147)
          - Models, undated (Box 30, Folder 148)
        - Cranbrook Institute of Science, Bloomfield Hills, MI
          - Brochures and reports, 1936, 1951, 1960, undated (Box 31, Folder 149)
          - Exteriors, undated (Box 31, Folder 150)
          - Floor plans, undated (Box 31, Folder 151)
          - Negatives, undated (Box 31, Folder 152)
          - Planetarium interior, undated (Box 31, Folder 153)
          - Rendering, undated (Box 31, Folder 154)
        - Cranbrook Pavilion, Bloomfield Hills, MI, 1935, undated (Box 31, Folder 155)
        - Kingswood School for Girls, Bloomfield Hills, MI
          - Exteriors, undated (Box 31, Folder 156 - 157)
          - Interiors, undated (Box 31, Folder 158)
          - Negatives, undated (Box 31, Folder 159)
    - Detroit Riverfront Plan [photograph of sketch], 1924 (Box 31, Folder 160)
    - Helsinki Post Office competition [photoreproductions of rendering, site plan, floor plan], 1934 (Box 31, Folder 161)
    - Helsinki Railroad Station [exterior photographs, interior rendering, map of city], Circa 1913 (Box 31, Folder 162)
    - Kalevale-talo, Finland [photoreproduction of rendering], 1921 (Box 31, Folder 163)
    - Lakefront Development, Chicago [photoreproductions of renderings and site plan], undated (Box 31, Folder 164)
    - League of Nations Palace proposal [photoreproductions of rendering], undated (Box 31, Folder 165)
    - Munksnas-Haga model [photograph of section by Loja Saarinen], [1912-1915] (Box 31, Folder 166)
    - Parliament House competition, Canberra, Australia [correspondence and compensation report], 1916-1925 (Box 31, Folder 167)
    - Tribune Tower competition, Chicago [photoreproductions of renderings], 1922 (Box 31, Folder 168)
    - Miscellaneous models,floor plans, furniture and artwork, 1941, undated (Box 31, Folder 169)
    - Miscellaneous renderings [photoreproductions, photographs, and negatives], 1922, undated (Box 31, Folder 170)
      - NJN: Eliel Saarinen rendering, 1925 (Box 675, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous award medals, 1957, 1958, 1966, undated (Box 19)
- Office Records, 1880-1985; 1951-1964; Series III
  The Office Records series is arranged by record type in eight subseries: Administrative records, Brochures, Correspondence, Financial records, Patent applications, Public Relations, Scrapbooks, and Works by others.
  Office records document those aspects of the firm's activities which were not directly related to the designing and constructing of buildings. Financial ledgers documenting how much time was spent on any particular project and who worked on it; publicity binders showcasing professional photographs of the completed buildings; relocation information gathered when moving the office from Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, to Hamden, Connecticut; patent applications and documentation for the Knoll furniture; and scrapbooks, pertaining to various projects and kept by various members of the firm are all located in Series III. This series also includes all materials pertaining to Joseph Lacy, Kevin Roche, and other associates in Saarinen's firm.
  Administrative records in this series comprise primarily relocation information collected by the firm when Saarinen announced he would be moving the firm from Bloomfield Hills, Michigan to Hamden, Connecticut. They include photographs and plans of the new office site, the Frederick Graves residence on Davis Street in Hamden; school and community information collected so that members of the firm could decide where to buy homes in the area; and press materials announcing the move.
  Brochures were either created by Saarinen's clients for publicity purposes, or were created by Eero Saarinen and Associates as part of their proposals in their bids to win particular commissions. Brochures created for inclusion in press packets or annual reports by the clients are part of this subseries. They differ from the brochures housed in Series IV, Project Records, which, in most cases, are presentation brochures created by Eero Saarinen and Associates to update their clients on the progress being made on a particular project.
  The small Correspondence subseries contains letters of condolence written to the surviving members of the firm after Saarinen's death, copies of some responses to those letters, and correspondence about legal issues surrounding Saarinen's estate.
  Financial records include job cost breakdowns for a number of the firm's projects, as well as some payroll records. The largest portion of this subseries is the time-cost ledgers, which document the date of a project's inception, the members of the firm that worked on the project and for how long, and the costs for each stage of the project. These records would be valuable to those researchers seeking exact dates for a project.
  The Patent application materials in Series III pertain to furniture designs by Saarinen that were later produced by Knoll and Heywood-Wakefield. Fabric samples, drawings, and photographs in support of these design and mechanical patent applications are contained in this subseries.
  The Public Relations subseries is further subdivided into three categories of material: General, Publicity binders, and Publicity photographs. Publicity binders were created by Eero Saarinen & Associates to show examples of their work to prospective clients. Typically, these binders are composed of several photographs of one or more projects after completion, as well as a reproduction of a plan or elevation and, occasionally, a bit of text describing the projects. Originally the binders were numbered from 1 through 9; these numbers and this order have been maintained, though binders have been taken apart and rehoused for preservation. The order of projects within each binder has been maintained. There is some duplication of photographs between these binders and the project photographs in Series IV. Some of the projects within the binders were begun after Saarinen's death by his surviving partners.
  The Publicity photographs were primarily commissioned by the firm to document completed projects. Ezra Stoller was the photographer responsible for many of these photographs; other photographers that were regularly hired by the firm include Baltazar Korab of Birmingham, Michigan and Hedrich-Blessing of Chicago. Many of these photographs, which are mounted on board, are duplicates of photographs already housed with the project records or in the Publicity binders.
  Scrapbooks are arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the first project within a given scrapbook. Some scrapbooks cover only one project; others cover several. The scrapbooks themselves were disassembled, photocopied for preservation purposes, and rehoused in individual folders, one scrapbook per folder. Therefore, many projects may be contained within a single scrapbook folder. Because scrapbooks were assembled at different times by different people, articles and projects may be duplicated across scrapbook folders.
  The final subseries, Works by others, is a collection of articles or manuscript drafts about Saarinen and his work written by researchers and kept with the firm's office records. Some of the texts, such as Eloise Engle's Finns in North America, only briefly mention Saarinen; other correspondence and writing, such as that between Aline Saarinen and Allan Temko while he was in the process of writing his biography of Saarinen, is much more substantial and revealing. These articles are part of Series III because they concern Saarinen and/or his oeuvre, rather than the clippings, part of Series IV, which concern only specific buildings.
  - Administrative records
    - Office relocation information
      - Hamden area school and community information, 1960-1961 (Box 32, Folder 1 - 2)
      - Photographs of existing site [Graves residence] before renovations, undated (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - Press releases and publicity material pertaining to office relocation, 1960-1961 (Box 32, Folder 4)
      - Office relocation, Hamden, CT: Drawings: site plan, elevations, floor plans of existing buidling (F.D. Graves residence), undated (Folder 684F)
      - Site plan for existing structure (F.D. Graves residence), undated (Box 676, Folder 86)
    - Photograph and publication inventories maintained by Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo and Associates, 1985 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Project lists, undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Slide lists, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Brochures
    - Art and Design at Concordia Senior College and A Guide to Concordia Senior College, Circa 1962-1963 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Building a Senior College: Progress Report on Concordia Senior College, Fort Wayne, Indiana, Circa 1954, 1956 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Guildings for Business and Government, Museum of Modern Art exhibition catalogue [includes General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI], 1957 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System Headquarters, New York, NY: booklet, 1964 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Columbus, Indiana: Athens of the Prairie and A Salute to Columbus Architecture, 1967-1968 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Dedication of the Gateway Arch: Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, Saint Louis, Missouri, May 25, 1968, program, related publications and memorabilia (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Deere & Company Headquarters, Moline, IL: booklets for opening ceremonies, June 4-5, 1964 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Detroit Civic Center, Master Plan: miscellaneous publications, 1946, 1947, 1951, undated (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Drake University: miscellaneous university publications, 1955, undated (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Dulles International Airport: Master Plan Report: Prepared for the Federal Aviation Agency, Washington, D.C., 1964 (Box 697, Folder 196)
    - Eero Saarinen and Associates: Air Force Academy, request-for-proposal brochure, undated (Box 697, Folder 197)
    - A Foundation for Learning: Planning the Campus of Brandeis University, Circa 1951 (Box 697, Folder 198)
    - General Motors Technical Center, undated (Box 697, Folder 199)
    - IBM Research Center, Eero Saarinen and Associates, Yorktown, NY, undated (Box 699, Folder 206)
    - Knoll Associates, Inc., Single Pedestal Furniture Designed by Eero Saarinen, undated (Box 32, Folder 16)
      - Additional Material (Box 710)
    - Metropolitan Milwaukee War Memorial Center: The Changing Picture -- Time for Decision: A Report and Recommendations by Eero Saarinen & Associates, Architects, Nov. 15, 1950 (Box 699, Folder 205)
    - No Vision Too Large: Proposed Residential Colleges for the University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois, 1955 (Box 699, Folder 207)
    - Repertory Theater of Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts: Prologue: 1963 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - The School of Music of the University of Michigan, 1964 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - This is IBM Rochester...A New Industry for Southeastern Minnesota, undated (Box 32, Folder 19)
    - TWA Proposed Terminal Building, New York International Airport, Eero Saarinen and Associates [includes two different covers], undated (Box 699, Folder 208)
    - The Trustees of the Estate of Henry H. Houston Present Land for Large Scale Development in Suburban Philadelphia, undated (Box 699, Folder 209)
    - University of Chicago Law School brochure, undated (Box 699, Folder 210)
    - Vassar College Main Hall renovation, undated (Box 699, Folder 211)
    - Where Today Meets Tomorrow [General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI], undated (Box 697, Folder 200)
    - Yale University: Study for College-Temple Block, 1964 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters of condolence, 1961-1962 (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - Saarinen estate, 1961-1967 (Box 33, Folder 22 - 23)
  - Financial
    - Financial audit, Eero Saarinen & Associates, 1952 (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - Job cost breakdowns, 1956-1958, undated (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Payroll costs, 1955-1966 (Box 33, Folder 26 - 27)
    - Time-cost ledgers
      - Jobs 5007 through 5606, 1950-1955 (Box 34, Folder 28 - 34)
      - Jobs 5606F through 5802-13, 1956-1957 (Box 35, Folder 35 - 41)
      - Jobs 5804F through 6010-X-17, 1958 (Box 36, Folder 42 - 49)
      - Saarinen, Saarinen and Associates ledger, 1947-1950 (Box 37)
      - "Job Costs", 1950-1961 (Box 38, Folder 50)
        See also: Series I. Personal Papers, 1920-2004 (inclusive), 1940-1961 (bulk) Box 2
      - Payroll, check registers, 1947-1962 (Box 38A, Folder 51, Box 38E, Folder 55, Box 38-F, Folder 56, Box 38G, Folder 57, Box 38B, Folder 52, Box 38C, Folder 53, Box 38D, Folder 54)
  - Patent applications
    - File 9095A: General (miscellaneous) files, 1951-1959 (Box 39, Folder 58 - 61)
    - File 9095B: General (miscellaneous) files, 1959-1961 (Box 39, Folder 62)
    - Docket #3503: Chair: Foreign design applications [Venezuela, Mexico, Cuba], 1956-1960 (Box 39, Folder 63)
    - Docket #3520: Chair: Mechanical patent #2,541,835, 1880-1882, 1927-1966 (Box 39, Folder 64 - 65)
    - Docket #3521: Chair: Mechanical patent #2,606,601, 1925-1967 (Box 39, Folder 66)
    - Docket #3522: Chair: Design patent #158,510, 1948-1950, 1956 (Box 39, Folder 67)
    - Docket #3535: Chair: Design patent #158,509, 1946-1957 (Box 40, Folder 68)
    - Docket #3662: Furniture and supports: Mechanical patent #2,939,517, 1847-1965 (Box 40, Folder 69 - 71)
    - Docket #3787: Chair: Design patent #181,946, 1954-1966 (Box 40, Folder 72)
    - Docket #3788: Chair: Design patent #181,945, 1934, circa1954-1966 (Box 40, Folder 73)
    - Docket #3901: Dining table: Design patent #187,797, 1957-1966 (Box 40, Folder 74)
    - Docket #3902: Coffee table: Design patent #187,798, 1957-1966 (Box 40, Folder 75)
    - Docket #3902: Coffee table: Design patent #187,798, 1943, circa1957-1960 (Box 41, Folder 76)
    - Docket #3904: Side table: Design patent #187,799, 1957-1966 (Box 41, Folder 77)
  - Public Relations
    - General
      - Biographical information: Eero Saarinen, Aline B. Saarinen, and John G. Dinkeloo, undated (Box 41, Folder 78)
      - Clippings, 1951-1958, 1961 (Box 673, Folder 39)
      - Correspondence with A + U [periodical], 1973-1974 (Box 41, Folder 79)
      - Exhibition panels for unidentified exhibition: negatives, 1960 (Box 41, Folder 80)
      - Firm histories, 1960-1965 (Box 41, Folder 81)
      - Publications record, undated (Box 41, Folder 82)
      - Requests for publicity materials, 1953, 1959-1962 (Box 41, Folder 83 - 86)
      - Script for video presentation on Eero Saarinen [posthumous], undated (Box 54, Folder 95)
    - Publicity binders
      - Binder #1, undated
        - Dulles International Airport, Chantilly, VA (Box 42)
        - United States Embassy Chancellery, London, England (Box 42)